Ely Samuel Parker Papers 1794-1946 Mss.497.3.P223
American Philosophical Society
Ely Samuel Parker Papers
1794-1946
Mss.497.3.P223
American Philosophical Society
1.75 Linear feet
A Sachem and Civil War adjutant to Ulysses Grant, Ely Samuel Parker was an important figure in the Seneca Indian nation during the first half of the nineteenth century. Trained as an engineer, Parker was deeply involved in the Senecas' land disputes with the Ogden Land Company and he played an important role in interpreting Seneca culture for a white audience, most notably as a consultant for Lewis Henry Morgan. Collected by Arthur C. Parker, the Ely Samuel Parker Papers include correspondence, manuscripts, and printed materials relating primarily to Seneca affairs, history, language, and culture, as well as politics, education, engineering, and the Civil War. Among Parker's correspondents were Henry Clay, Millard Fillmore, Henry M. Flagler, Lewis Henry Morgan, Henry Rowe Schoolcraft, Daniel Webster, and Asher Wright. Several letters relate to Parker's service as engineer of public buildings in Galena, Illinois, and to his Masonic activities. Among the noteworthy items in the collection are several essays on Seneca history and culture, a fragment of Parker's diary, 1847, and a significant quantity of material on the Seneca language assembled by Asher Wright.
Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895
Existence and Location of Copies note
FILM 1381
General note
Much of this was used in: G.S.Snyderman "Function of Wampum in Iroquois Religion", APS Proceedings, vol.105, 571-608.
Bibliography
Arthur C. Parker, The Life of General Ely S. Parker: Last Grand Sachem of the Iroquois and General Grant's Military Secretary (Buffalo, N.Y., 1919).
Armstrong, William H., Warrior in Two Camps: Ely S. Parker, Union General and Seneca Chief (Syracuse, N.Y., 1978).
Early American History Note
The Ely Parker Collection is a large and rich amalgamation of documents relating to the New York Seneca and to Ely Parker’s own life.
The earliest documents often involve Asher Wright, a missionary, and reflect his experience with Indians on and around Buffalo Creek. There is a fair amount of information on language included in this portion of the collection.
Ely Parker’s own correspondence includes a large amount of material relating to the Treaty of Buffalo Creek, including petitions sent to Congress and records of the negotiations. There are various documents on the legal case challenging the Treaty throughout the 1840s, including Parker’s advice to fight against the treaty’s implementation.
In addition to the discussions about the controversial treaty, there are interesting documents in Parker’s own hand, including a letter on injustice, a fragment of a creation story, a fair amount of information on Indian education, and fragments of essays Parker wrote on Indian history, culture, and Christianity.
The collection also has various essays and compositions written by others, likely by students at a missionary school.
The collection in particularly strong for the period from 1840 to 1860. In addition to providing insight on Seneca history, there are documents on engineering, which Parker undertook after receiving a degree from Renssellaer Polytechnic University.
Related Archival Materials note
See also the Ely Samuel Parker Papers (A.P24), Rare Books and Special Collections Department, University of Rochester.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Arthur C. Parker, 1950.
Scope and Contents note
The Ely Parker Papers provide outstanding documentation for one of the best known Seneca leaders of the 19th century. Rich in information on Seneca history, culture, and language and on Parker's varied activities in both the Indian and white worlds, the collection is a major resource for examining the land and political struggles of the Seneca nation during the 1840s and early 1850s. Comprised of a mix of personal and professional correspondence augmented by a smaller quantity of printed materials, notes, and manuscripts, the collection is arranged chronologically. It is richest for the period 1845-1860, with only a few letters pertaining to Parker's Civil War service, and even fewer for the post-war period.
From 1843 through 1848, the Parker Papers provide excellent documentation of the legal battles to resolve the Ogden Land Company's claims to Seneca lands and Seneca efforts to prevent white encroachment. Several letters in 1847 describe the misfortunes of those Senecas who agreed to migrate to the West. Although Parker remained deeply involved in Seneca legal and political affairs after 1848, he appears to have become increasingly consumed with his engineering duties.
Through his interest in Seneca history and culture, Parker accumulated a number of manuscripts of Asher Wright, the missionary at Tonanwanda, a student of the Seneca language, and a long acquaintance of Parker's. These deal primarily with Seneca grammar, conjugations of verbs, vocabulary, and orthography, but also include translations of scripture, an address interlineated in English and Seneca on the mission boarding school, and most importantly, an 1840 census of the Senecas residing at Buffalo, organized in tabular form by clan. Most of Wright's monographs on the Seneca language are available in the Printed Materials Department. Parker's correspondence with his siblings Caroline, Nicholas, and Newton, provides insight into their education and their personal relationships, and includes a brief essay written by Caroline Parker in 1850 on the prophet Handsome Lake.
As an major consultant to Lewis Henry Morgan and a correspondent of Henry Rowe Schoolcraft, Parker's correspondence includes a number of letters pertaining to Seneca culture and to the early culture of American ethnography. While his Civil War experiences are not particularly well documented, there are three letters and a map from Newton Parker, serving in the 132nd New York Infantry at New Bern, N.C., and half a dozen letters from Ely Parker, including two written during the Chattanooga Campaign.
Finally, the collection also contains a manuscript copy of a work said to be Seth Newhouse's Legend of Dekanawida, 1885.
Native American Images note: Eleven images, primarily of Ely Samuel Parker and his family members. Includes some early photographs, particularly an undated daguerreotype of Parker’s father, William. Also of note, a 1920 rotogravure of an 1864 reprint of General Ulysses S. Grant and his staff in camp. In oversize, 1844 printed map of the 12,800 acre tract in the Tonnewanda (sic) Reservation.
Biographical/Historical note
A sachem of the Seneca nation, adjutant to Ulysses S. Grant during the Civil War, and a political and cultural intermediary, Ely Samuel Parker (Hasanoanda) was a pivotal figure in the Seneca nation during the second quarter of the 19th century. Born on the Tonawanda Reservation in western New York in 1828, the son of Elizabeth Johnson and William Parker, Ely Parker was educated at a Baptist mission school and at the Cayuga Academy in Aurora, N.Y. A bright and articulate young man, he was well respected by his elders and was rewarded with positions of responsibility early in life. His teenage years were a time of crisis for the Seneca nation, which was beset on all sides by white settlers and by the specious claims on their land by the Ogden Land Company. Parker took on the struggle, serving as an intermediary with the federal government during negotiations over the Buffalo Creek treaties of 1838 and 1842, and he represented the Senecas in other legal and political affairs. Parker was elevated to sachem in 1852, assuming the name Donehogawa previously held by John Blacksmith.
Parker's name in the white world was also established early. Before he turned 20, he met the protoethnologist Lewis Henry Morgan and became a principal consultant in preparation of the League of the Ho-Dé-No-Sau-Nee (Rochester, 1851), and through Morgan he gained access to the wider white world of intellectuals and politicians. With training as an engineer, Parker garnered positions on public canal projects throughout the state, seeing his circle of acquaintances steadily expand. He took a warm interest in partisan politics in New York, joining both the freemasons and the militia as well as Morgan's Grand Council of the Iroquois to further himself. Both he and his brother Nicholas were also regularly engaged to lecture on Seneca history and culture to white audiences, becoming recognized as authorities.
In 1857, Parker was hired to assist in the construction of the new custom house in Galena, Ill., where he befriended a relatively obscure army officer, Ulysses S. Grant. The Grant connection would serve Parker well. Although Parker's attempts to join the army at the outbreak of the Civil War were repeatedly rebuffed, first because of his engineering obligations and later because he was an Indian, he finally succeeded in securing a commission as Captain of Engineers in 1863. By the end of that year, he was assigned to duty on Grant's staff. Following Grant from Chattanooga to Virginia, Parker was given the honor at Appomattox of writing down the terms of surrender for the Army of Northern Virginia, and was brevetted Brigadier General for his services in 1865. He married a white woman, Minnie Sackett, on Christmas day, 1867.
Following Grant's election to the presidency, Parker was appointed Commissioner of Indian Affairs on April 13, 1869. During a controversial three year tenure, he spearheaded Grant's "peace plan," essentially abolishing the treaty system in favor of Christianization and assimilation and emphasizing the mutual responsibility of the federal government and the Indian nations in preserving peace. Political opposition to these policies plagued Parker, however, and his opponents leveled charges of fraud against him in Congress. Although he was acquitted, Parker resigned his post in 1871, and with his finances damaged in the Panic of 1873, he spent the last years of his life in Fairfield, Conn., in relative obscurity and poverty.
Having suffered for years from diabetes, Parker died after a lengthy decline on August 30, 1895. He was buried at Oak Lawn Cemetery in Fairfield, Conn., but was reinterred in Forest Lawn Cemetery in Buffalo on January 20, 1897, and is now situated near several other Seneca notables, including Red Jacket. Ironically, forty five years previously Parker had vehemently protested the reinterment of Red Jacket's bones in this same cemetery.
Clay, Henry, 1777-1852; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874; Flagler, Henry M.; Ga-i-wah-go-wa, [Parker, N. H.]; Handsome Lake, 1735-1815; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881; Mountpleasant, Caroline Parker; Newhouse, Seth; Parker, Caroline; Parker, Newton I.; Parker, Nicholas; Parker, Spencer Cone; Parker, William H.; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852; Wright, Asher, 1803-1875; Canals--New York (State); Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Eastern Woodlands Indians; Education; Engineers--New York (State); Freemasons--New York (State); General Correspondence; Government Affairs; Iroquois Indians; Language and Linguistics; Language Material; Law; Manuscript Essays; Maps.; Military History; Native America; Native American Materials; New York (State)--Politics and government--19th century; Official Government Documents and Records; Ogden Land Company; Portrait photographs; Religion; Science and Technology; Seneca Indians--Missions; Seneca Indians--New York (State); Seneca Indians--Religion; Seneca language; Society of Friends--Relations with Indians; Tonawanda Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Tonawanda, (N.Y.)--Maps; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
- Series I. Correspondence, 1794-1946; 1.5 linear feet
  - LS to Handsome Lake and Cornplanter, [1794?]; [U.S. Secretary of War?] (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Transcript of part of an address delivered on the occasion of presenting "a written instrument, which is to be considered as a General Guarantee of all the lands within the United States to which you are entitled..."
  - Roster of Tonawanda veterans War of 1812 (Box 1)
    Typed copy of original in the Huntington Library.
  - LS to Secretary of War, 1815 Feb. 20; Iroquois Chiefs (Box 1)
    Communication listing losses of men and property in the War of 1812. Typed copy of original in the University of Rochester library.
  - ANS to John Greig, 1829 May 7; Fellows, Joseph, 1782-1873 (Box 1)
    Brief note stating "on the 18 May at noon the books will be opened for subscriptions," written on verso of printed announcement concerning estimated revenue to be derived from Sodus Canal.
  - Pr. Memorial to U.S. Congress, 1829 Nov.; Sodus Canal Subscribers (Box 1)
    Printed memorial from inhabitants of Wayne, Cayuga, Seneca and Ontario counties, concerning advantages of a connection between Erie Canal and Great Sodus Bay.
  - Linguistic exercises, 1833 Jan. 7; [Wright, Asher] (Box 1)
    Seneca "verb to love, ganoongwaseh, conjugated through all its variations and tenses."
  - Linguistic exercises, 1833 Jan. 16; [Wright, Asher] (Box 1)
    Conjugation of the verb `redeem' in Seneca.
  - Linguistic exercise, 1833 Jan. 28; [Wright, Asher?] (Box 1)
    Conjugation of the Seneca verb ohgadeies, to learn, study or teach.
  - Notebook, 1833 Aug. 22; [Wright, Asher?] (Box 1)
    Notebook containing partial conjugations in Seneca of the following verbs: come, live or abide, walk, arise and awake.
  - Linguistic exercise, [1833?]; [?] and [Asher Wright?] (Box 1)
    Conjugation of the verbs 'repent' and `punish' (1) in Seneca, and (2) in Seneca with English. The latter is in two handwritings.
  - Memorandum of hours spent at the Seneca Mission... Oct. 14-21, 1834 Oct. 22; Harris, Thompson S. (Box 1)
    Verso contains a brief Seneca text without English translation.
  - LS to Chiefs of the Cattaraugus Reservation, 1834 Nov. 27; James Harris, Thompson S. Harris, Joseph A. Sanford et al. (Box 1)
    Part of a letter in the Seneca language. Two signatures are not fully decipherable.
  - 1835 June 5, [Wright, Asher?] (Box 1)
    Seneca and English names for months, inscribed at "Seneca Mission House."
  - Seneca word list and text, 1836 Apr. 5 (Box 1)
    Single sheet, inscribed at Cattaraugus Mission, containing brief Seneca-English word list and a Seneca text without translation.
  - AL to Sister Stone, 1836 June 23; [?] (Box 1)
    Unfinished letter from a lonely missionary at Buffalo Reservation, in which mention is made of Brother Wright, Father Williams, and Sister Lee. Verso contains Seneca-English vocabulary and notation about cost of trip from Buffalo to Tuscarora, Rochester, Syracuse and other points.
  - DS to S. Bliss and J. Tuttle, 1836 Nov. 10; Hill, J. (Box 1)
    I.O.U.for $11.00.
  - ALS to Asher Wright, 1837 Dec. 7; Schermerhorn, I. F. (Box 1)
    Letter accusing Wright of interfering with treaty and discouraging Seneca emigration.
  - TLS Cy to T. L. Ogden and J. Fellows, 1838 June 23; O. Allen, H. P. Wilcox, J. Stryker and H. P. Potter (Box 1)
    Typed copy of letter re. expenses connected with securing title to Indian lands.
  - TLS Cy to Thomas L. Ogden, 1838 June 24; Potter, H. B. (Box 1)
    Typed copy of a letter requesting $5,000 for services as an agent of the Ogden Land Co. over a 15 year period.
  - TLS Cy to Joseph Fellows, 1838 June 27; Ogden, Thomas L. (Box 1)
    Typed copy of letter concerning payments to agents.
  - ALS to Spencer H. Cone, 1838 July 3; Fellows, Joseph, 1782-1873 (Box 1)
    Letter concerning treaty ratified on June 11, 1838
  - LS to Henry Clay, 1838?; 2p.; Two Guns (Box 1)
    Letter in handwriting of Asher Wright asking help that treaty may not be ratified.
  - "Missionary Notes", 1838 ?; 30p.; [Wright, Asher] (Box 1)
    A Seneca word book, arranged alphabetically, with English equivalents.
  - Petition to U.S. Congress, 25th, 3d session., 1839 Jan. 30; Seneca Nation of New York (Box 1)
    Printed "petition of a delegation of the Seneca Indians, stating that unfair means had been used to obtain the assent of the Indians to the treaty as negotiated with the New York Indians, and amended by the Senate, and praying that the Senate may suspend action upon the said treaty."
  - Memorial to U.S. Congress, 25th, 3d session., 1839 Feb. 9; Seneca Nation of New York (Box 1)
    Printed "Memorial of a delegation of the Seneca Indians, protesting against the ratification of the treaty made with the New York Indians, as amended by the Senate..."
  - DS with David Finly, 1839 Mar. 21; Tonawanda Chiefs (Box 1)
    Agreement, selling rights to gypsum.
  - Minutes at Council of the Six Nations, 1839 July 17; 21p.; Wright, Asher (Box 1)
    Minutes, and list of chiefs elected and inaugurated, at a Council of the Six Nations, held at the Onondaga Council House.
  - Notebook, 1839?; [Wright, Asher] (Box 1)
    Notebook with a number of blank leaves, containing about 4p. of Seneca-English words and phrases, and about 8p. of brief comments on the organization of the Iroquois League.
  - Notebook, 183?; 23p.; [Wright, Asher] (Box 1)
    Notebook on the Seneca language containing names for days of the week; terms for God; numerals 1 to 30; an English-Seneca word list; pronouns; and miscellaneous notes on the article "ne" and on prefixes and suffixes denoting person, gender, quantity, etc. Notebook was made by folding and cutting sheets of paper, on one of which appears the first line of a letter dated Aug. 27, 1837, at Andover Theological Seminary.
  - T. Hartly Crawford to George Jimseon, 1840 May 27 (Box 1)
    Letter refusing petition for money to be applied toward the education of Jimeson's son, John.
  - TDfS Cy to U.S. Government, 1840; Council of the Seneca Nation (Box 1)
    Typewritten copy of a draft of a petition giving Indian views of treaty.
  - Notebooks, 1840; 27p. and 22p.; [Wright, Asher?] (Box 1)
    Two notebooks, each containing English and Indian names of over 300 Senecas residing at Buffalo, arranged by clans, and giving the following information in tabular form: place of birth, age, number of children, sex, religion and rank.
  - Address, ca.1842; [Parker, Nicholson H.?] (Box 1)
    Part of an address dealing with proceedings at various councils held prior to ratification of treaties of 1838 and 1842.
  - A Spelling Book (part), 1842; [Wright, Asher] (Box 1)
    Manuscript for Lesson XXXII, p. 25 and part of Lesson XXXIII, p. 26 of the 1842 edition of "A Spelling Book..."
  - A Spelling Book in the Seneca Language, 1842; Disbound; Wright, Asher (Box 1)
    "A Spelling-Book in the Seneca Language: with English definitions." Buffalo-Creek Reservation, Mission Press, 1842.
  - ALS to Nicholson Parker, 1843 Feb. 23; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    Letter listing Indian objects which Ely would like to have sent to him at Yates school.
  - AMs, 1843 Feb. 28; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    Fragment of an address at Yates Academy.
  - AMs, 1843 Sept. 20; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    An address to the Englopian Society.
  - LS to James B. Porter, 1843 Oct. 24; Tonawanda Chiefs (Box 1)
    Letter to the Secretary of War, stating that Thomas C. Love and Ira Cook were prevented from appraising Tonawanda improvements and incorporating remarks passed at a council on Oct. 23.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1843 Oct. 29; Parker, Caroline (Box 1)
    Letter containing news of studies and school friends and thoughts on Christianity.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1843 Nov. 28; Moseley, William A. (Box 1)
    Brief acknowledgement of Parker's letter of November 24, and of the accompanying papers, stating "I shall take pleasure in laying them before the Secretary of War and commending your application to his favor."
  - ALS to Thomas C. Cook and Ira Love, 1844 Jan. 4; Crawford, T. Hartly. (Box 1)
    Letter stating official view of the Office of Indian Affairs on the legal implications of the Seneca strategy in preventing an appraisement of the improvements on their land.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1844 Jan. 6; Moseley, William A. (Box 1)
    Letter reporting interview with Commissioner of Indian Affairs and enclosing reply from Commissioner, asking Ely to make copy of same and return original.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1844 Jan. 19; Moseley, William A. (Box 1)
    Letter stating President must enforce treaties.
  - ALS to William Parker, 1844 Jan. 29; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    Letter advising his father that since the Government has no power to enforce treaty, the Indians should repel those who attempt to remove them from their present homes.
  - Address, 1844 Feb. 6; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    Address before Englopian Society.
  - Ams essay, 1844 Apr. 29; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    "There is nothing so harsh upon the ear...as the simple word composition," written at Yates Academy.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1844 May 8 and 22; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 1)
    Letter with postscript and photostat of same stating that Parker has been elected member of the Grand Order of the Iroquois.
  - ALS to Chiefs Blacksmith and Jimmy Johnson, 1844 June 17; Bouck, William C. (Box 1)
    Letter from Governor of New York stating he has no power to interfere in Ogden dispute and advising legal procedure to follow in contesting the land company's schemes.
  - Map, 1844 Aug. 19; Ogden Land Company (Box OS)
    Map of the 12,800 acre tract on the Tonawanda Reservation, with location of lots to be sold at auction in Batavia.
  - ALS to [Tonawanda Chiefs?], 1844 Sept. 5; Palfrey, John G. (Box 1)
    Acknowledgment by the Secretary of State's Office of a letter dated Aug. 27 addressed to the Governor of Massachusetts, and requesting more specific details concerning complaint.
  - ALS to John Blacksmith, James Johnson and others., 1844 Oct. 12; Palfrey, John G. (Box 1)
    Handwritten copy of a reply to their letter of Sept. 30 requesting an interview with the Governor, stating the government of Massachusetts had no right to intervene between the Indians and the Ogden Land Co.
  - DS to John Bigfire and H. Nicholson Parker., 1844?; Tonawanda Chiefs (Box 1)
    Power of attorney signed by chiefs and warriors.
  - AMs Cy, 1844?; Bronson, Judge (Box 1)
    Transcript of the remarks of the Judge of the Supreme Court of New York, concerning title to Indian lands on which timber was out.
  - to Silas Wright, 1845 Feb. 22; Tonawanda Chiefs (Box 1)
    An appeal to the Governor of New York for justice to prevent Whites from settling on Indian lands until difficulties with the Ogden Co. are settled.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1845 Feb. 25; Warren, R. B. (Box 1)
    Letter from a school friend chatting about the writer's return to Yates, injustice to the Indian, etc.
  - School accounts, 1845 Mar. 31; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    Accounting of expenses at Yates, first quarter. Verso has essay on "the study of man."
  - Poem, "My Brother Solomon", 1845 May?; Parker, Caroline (Box 1)
    A poem about a dead brother.
  - Minutes of meeting of Baptist churches, 1845 June 28; Parker, Levi (Box 1)
    Minutes of meeting of Baptist churches at Tuscarora, Tonawanda, and Grand River.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1845 Aug. 8; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864 (Box 1)
    Letter reporting on cooperation accorded the writer at Tuscarora.
  - ALS to Spencer H. Cone, 1845 Aug. 30; Parker, William and Williams, James. (Box 1)
    Letters to Spencer who has emigrated to Missouri from his father and uncle. William Parker's letter states "your youngest brother...Solomon...died the 23rd of last May." Both letters contain family and reservation news and hearty endorsements of Christianity.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1845 Oct. 19; Parsons, S. (Box 1)
    Flowery letter acknowledging a note of Oct. 9th, in which Parker informed Parsons fate had decreed against his attending Wilson Collegiate Institute.